<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transportation on Mountain Doodles</title>
    <link>/categories/transportation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Transportation on Mountain Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/transportation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Transit Explorer</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/</guid>
      <description>I have played with Mapzen&amp;rsquo;s Isochrone serivce in the past with a simple visualization of walksheds.
Recently Mazen updated the isochrone API to allow for a more fine-grained selection of exactly what transit services to include or exclude in transit routing, and they created an amazing mobility explorer based on that.
Partially motivated by chatting with two TransLink planners I decided to riff off of that and take a look at how well TransLink serves different parts of Vancouver.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TOD</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/04/06/tod/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/04/06/tod/</guid>
      <description>Just saw this excellent post looking at density around transit stations today and though I should pull out some numbers to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&amp;rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data estimates it&amp;rsquo;s super-easy to do.
Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or amenities density would be others. But for now let&amp;rsquo;s focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surrey Traffic Loop Counts</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/03/27/surrey-traffic-loop-counts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/03/27/surrey-traffic-loop-counts/</guid>
      <description>Surrey published a beta version of their traffic loop counts, which is pretty awesome. Real life traffic data is very exciting, and there are lots of fun things one could do with that. So last night I decided to take a look and make a quick map. Nothing exciting yet, just to feel may way around what&amp;rsquo;s there. To keep things simple I again took advantage of the awesome Tangram mapping enginge and turned it onto the traffic loop data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Land Use, Roads (and Parking)</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/</guid>
      <description>The other day at the SFU&amp;rsquo;s City Conversations someone asked a question about space dedicated to roads, and how that could be unlocked to aid housing. He mentioned what percentage of space is currently dedicated to roads. I forgot the number, but I thought to myself that I should look that up for all Metro Vancouver communities. So here we go. Actually, it would be interesting to compare how land is allocated to all kinds of land uses across Metro Vancouver, not just roads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hidden Mortgage</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/08/25/the-hidden-mortgage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/08/25/the-hidden-mortgage/</guid>
      <description>Some months ago I did a little side project and put some Census Canada data for Vancouver on an interactive map online. After it generated quite some interest, to a large part due to Ian Young&amp;rsquo;s reporting utilizing some of the data in the South China Morning Post, I talked to my friend Alejandro and we decided to set up a Census Mapper that allowes laymen to map any census variables of their choosing Canada wide.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>