<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CensusMapper on Mountain Doodles</title>
    <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/categories/censusmapper/</link>
    <description>Recent content in CensusMapper on Mountain Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/categories/censusmapper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>dot-density</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/24/dot-density/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/24/dot-density/</guid>
      <description>I started writing this blog post in December 2015, when CensusMapper quite a bit younger and I hacked together some basic dot-density maps. I never much liked the results and have been slowly improving and thinking about them. I am still not entirely happy with the current implementation, but it is slowly getting there. The final impulse to finsish this post was the work on cancensus, and R wrapper for the CensusMapper API my explorations in multi-category dot density maps in R, now tied up into the new dotdensity package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/</guid>
      <description>Density in Vancouver has been one of the recurring themese on this blog, and there are many different ways to come at it. We have looked at density in terms of land use to understand how much land is devoted to what purpose in Metro Vancouver and it&amp;rsquo;s municipalities. We have looked at density in terms of tax density to understand how property tax revenue depends on land use and zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Millennials Redux</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/06/millennials-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/06/millennials-redux/</guid>
      <description>Catching up with my local news reading last night I stumbled about another new report on millennials.
The notion that millennials are fleeing Vancouver is a recurring theme in the Vancouver press, and we have addressed some of the problems in the data used to support that claim before.
Sadly, this new article&amp;rsquo;s use of data is no less problematic, and the topic, as well as the data misrepresentations, are serious enough that I felt they need addressing so as not do distract from the actual real problems that millennials are facing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifeblood</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood/</guid>
      <description>Ever since that Bloomberg article whose claims nobody could reproduce, where the author refused to disclose what data was used, but that got recycled all across the local press there has been a hightened interest in migration patterns in Vancouver. Nathan Lauster took it upon himself to dig deeper and look if Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s lifeblood was really leaving, which he kept elaborating on as better data became available until the most recent iteration that compares Metro Vancouver to other Candian metropolitan areas as well as the City of Vancouver to other cities within Metro Vancouver using 2016 census data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surprise Maps</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/10/surprise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 08:43:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/10/surprise/</guid>
      <description>At CensusMapper we like building models based on census data. We now have a common tiling for 2011 and 2016 geographies that allows us to easily model changes over time. After building a model we often want to see how well the model performs. An easy way to do this is to simply map the difference of observations and model predictions.
Those maps are great and it is easy to understand what is mapped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marine Gateway and Joyce-Collingwood</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood/</guid>
      <description>There has been some recent confusion that got confounded further about transit-oriented development in Vancouver harbouring a large number of non-primary residence homes. Good data is important in moving forward in Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s crazy housing market. Without proper context, a couple of data points can serve to paint a very misleading picture of what is happening. So I decided to fill in some gaps on the very narrow question of understanding the CT level numbers that get tossed around.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Censuses</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s great to have fresh census data to play with. Right now we only have three variables, population, dwellings and households. There is still lots of interesting information that can be extracted.
So we started exploring in our last post, things get really interesting when looking at change between censuses. But as we noted, there are several technical difficulties that need to be overcome.
So we at CensusMapper took that as and invitation to do what we love most: breaking down barriers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RS Population Change</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/</guid>
      <description>With reporting on the new census numbers gaining traction, and now Mayor Robertson picking up on single family neighbourhoods losing population we thought it is time to crunch some numbers.
Why does it need number crunching? All the reporting so far is based on looking at CT (Census Tract) aggregates, like e.g. in the map shown and linked to the right. But there is actually no single CT in the City of Vancouver that only contains RS zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 Census Data - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/</guid>
      <description>Finally the first batch of 2016 census data has arrived on Tuesday AM and CensusMapper was updated with the new census numbers by mid-morning.
Dissemination Block data was a little harder to find, but with the help of some friendly StatCan people I finally managed to locate the data and add that too this afternoon.
Time for writing up some observations. I am hoping to find time to do this regularly as more data gets released.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mixing Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/</guid>
      <description>Census data is very rich and with CensusMapper we now have about 1 billion data points right at our fingertips. And we have managed to open up some of our interfaces for everyone to explore data and make their own maps and freely share them.
Things really get interesting when one mixes custom data with census data. While, at this point, these are not part of the freely available CensusMapper functionality we still wanted to share what can be done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Mapping for Everyone</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/</guid>
      <description>At CensusMapper, we have come a long way from first dabbling in census data to building out a platform to map data Canada wide, adding the ability to easily drill down into individual census regions, improving mapping efficiency, adding the ability to automatically populate custom geographic data with census variables and adding older census data.
We believe all of these are comparatively small steps compared to the opening up of map making capabilities for everyone that we are rolling out today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Week</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week/</guid>
      <description>At CensusMapper we are super excited about Census Week 2016. Data is increasingly getting incorporated into local and regional decision making. At CensusMapper we have been working to facilitate this by making this wealth of information more accessible to everyone. To celebrate Census Week 2016 we have updated CensusMapper with 2006 census data for easy comparisons with the 2011 data. And we have given CensusMapper a face lift by adding a histogram widget that interacts with the mapping data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TOD Mode Share</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/</guid>
      <description>Just saw a comment on the Pricetags blog pointing to a nice master&amp;rsquo;s thesis investigating various TOD metrics around skytrain stations. I got curious how the 2011 transit mode share compares to the earlier census years listed in the thesis. And how the mode share varies spatially.
With CensusMapper at my finger tips and building on the visuals from the previous post this is an easy exercise.
We again simply map our concentric circles around the stations, but this time we turn them into pie charts to show the commute to work mode share.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TOD</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/</guid>
      <description>Just saw this excellent post looking at density around transit stations today and though I should pull out some numbers to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&amp;rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data estimates it&amp;rsquo;s super-easy to do.
Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or amenities density would be others. But for now let&amp;rsquo;s focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unoccupied Dwellings</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings/</guid>
      <description>Today the City of Vancouver released their report on unoccupied dwelling units in the city. I watched part of the presentation and read through the report, and from all that I can see the methodology used is very solid.
I have seen some confusion and even some incorrect reporting on this, so I thought it would be worthwhile to look into the report in detail. The Data Smart meter data can be used to determine very accurately which units are occupied and which ones are not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work vs Twiddling Thumbs</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/</guid>
      <description>In the ongoing debate on affordability of housing in the City of Vancouver we regularly hear voices expressing concern for &amp;ldquo;elderly folks of modest means who had been counting on using their home as a pension&amp;rdquo; to argue against doing anything to ease the housing affordability problems many (younger) people are facing. In these arguments the concern for &amp;ldquo;elderly folks of modest means&amp;rdquo; seems curiously focused to those who own property as opposed to, for example, the 20% of the elderly people in Vancouver that live in poverty (15k total).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Canvas vs SVG</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg/</guid>
      <description>CensusMapper Behind the Scenes The idea behind CensusMapper is that it takes away all the technical barriers to dealing with census data. So how does CensusMapper work behind the scenes?
CensusMapper Data Workflow The general setup is quite simple. We use the lean javascript open mapping platform leaflet as the base for mapping information. Leaflet handles the logic of dealing with zoom and pan and keeping track of the geographic boundaries that should be mapped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Drilldown</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/</guid>
      <description>Next steps in CensusMapper The Census Mapper Project is moving along slowly, public beta unearthed some bugs and we gathered feedback (thanks to everyone reporting back!). There are still a couple of steps that need to be taken care of before we can unleash the full map making power to all users. We feel that the complexity of census data requires more guidance than the current map making system is providing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Mapper</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce CensusMapper public beta launch! The project on mapping census data for Canada is entering the next stage. We are now mapping 3875 different variables from the 2011 census, or any combination of them, across 67215 geographic regions covering all of Canada.
We are opening up the Census Mapper to a limited public beta. Limited means that anyone can view maps created in CensusMapper, but we are only opening up the map creation tools to selected beta users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hidden Mortgage</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/08/25/the-hidden-mortgage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/08/25/the-hidden-mortgage/</guid>
      <description>Some months ago I did a little side project and put some Census Canada data for Vancouver on an interactive map online. After it generated quite some interest, to a large part due to Ian Young&amp;rsquo;s reporting utilizing some of the data in the South China Morning Post, I talked to my friend Alejandro and we decided to set up a Census Mapper that allowes laymen to map any census variables of their choosing Canada wide.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>