<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Mountain Doodles</title>
    <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Mountain Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>dot-density</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/24/dot-density/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/24/dot-density/</guid>
      <description>I started writing this blog post in December 2015, when CensusMapper quite a bit younger and I hacked together some basic dot-density maps. I never much liked the results and have been slowly improving and thinking about them. I am still not entirely happy with the current implementation, but it is slowly getting there. The final impulse to finsish this post was the work on cancensus, and R wrapper for the CensusMapper API my explorations in multi-category dot density maps in R, now tied up into the new dotdensity package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/</guid>
      <description>Density in Vancouver has been one of the recurring themese on this blog, and there are many different ways to come at it. We have looked at density in terms of land use to understand how much land is devoted to what purpose in Metro Vancouver and it&amp;rsquo;s municipalities. We have looked at density in terms of tax density to understand how property tax revenue depends on land use and zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Millennials Redux</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/06/millennials-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/06/millennials-redux/</guid>
      <description>Catching up with my local news reading last night I stumbled about another new report on millennials.
The notion that millennials are fleeing Vancouver is a recurring theme in the Vancouver press, and we have addressed some of the problems in the data used to support that claim before.
Sadly, this new article&amp;rsquo;s use of data is no less problematic, and the topic, as well as the data misrepresentations, are serious enough that I felt they need addressing so as not do distract from the actual real problems that millennials are facing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lifeblood</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/05/16/lifeblood/</guid>
      <description>Ever since that Bloomberg article whose claims nobody could reproduce, where the author refused to disclose what data was used, but that got recycled all across the local press there has been a hightened interest in migration patterns in Vancouver. Nathan Lauster took it upon himself to dig deeper and look if Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s lifeblood was really leaving, which he kept elaborating on as better data became available until the most recent iteration that compares Metro Vancouver to other Candian metropolitan areas as well as the City of Vancouver to other cities within Metro Vancouver using 2016 census data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surprise Maps</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/10/surprise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 08:43:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/10/surprise/</guid>
      <description>At CensusMapper we like building models based on census data. We now have a common tiling for 2011 and 2016 geographies that allows us to easily model changes over time. After building a model we often want to see how well the model performs. An easy way to do this is to simply map the difference of observations and model predictions.
Those maps are great and it is easy to understand what is mapped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marine Gateway and Joyce-Collingwood</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/04/03/joyce-collingwood/</guid>
      <description>There has been some recent confusion that got confounded further about transit-oriented development in Vancouver harbouring a large number of non-primary residence homes. Good data is important in moving forward in Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s crazy housing market. Without proper context, a couple of data points can serve to paint a very misleading picture of what is happening. So I decided to fill in some gaps on the very narrow question of understanding the CT level numbers that get tossed around.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Censuses</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/22/comparing-censuses/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s great to have fresh census data to play with. Right now we only have three variables, population, dwellings and households. There is still lots of interesting information that can be extracted.
So we started exploring in our last post, things get really interesting when looking at change between censuses. But as we noted, there are several technical difficulties that need to be overcome.
So we at CensusMapper took that as and invitation to do what we love most: breaking down barriers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RS Population Change</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/06/rs-population-change/</guid>
      <description>With reporting on the new census numbers gaining traction, and now Mayor Robertson picking up on single family neighbourhoods losing population we thought it is time to crunch some numbers.
Why does it need number crunching? All the reporting so far is based on looking at CT (Census Tract) aggregates, like e.g. in the map shown and linked to the right. But there is actually no single CT in the City of Vancouver that only contains RS zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transit Explorer</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/</guid>
      <description>I have played with Mapzen&amp;rsquo;s Isochrone serivce in the past with a simple visualization of walksheds.
Recently Mazen updated the isochrone API to allow for a more fine-grained selection of exactly what transit services to include or exclude in transit routing, and they created an amazing mobility explorer based on that.
Partially motivated by chatting with two TransLink planners I decided to riff off of that and take a look at how well TransLink serves different parts of Vancouver.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More on Teardowns</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/21/more-on-teardowns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/21/more-on-teardowns/</guid>
      <description>A little over a year ago we ran some analysis on teardowns of single family homes in the City of Vancouver. We used the City of Vancouver open data to understand why some single family homes got torn down and other&amp;rsquo;s don&amp;rsquo;t.
Relying entirely on open data, there were some important questions that could not be answered. So together with Joe Dahmen at UBC&amp;rsquo;s School Of Architecture And Landscape Architecture we came back to the question and folded in transaction data from BC Assessment to add some more details and rigor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 Census Data - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/02/10/2016-census-data/</guid>
      <description>Finally the first batch of 2016 census data has arrived on Tuesday AM and CensusMapper was updated with the new census numbers by mid-morning.
Dissemination Block data was a little harder to find, but with the help of some friendly StatCan people I finally managed to locate the data and add that too this afternoon.
Time for writing up some observations. I am hoping to find time to do this regularly as more data gets released.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jane Jacobs&#39; Vancouver</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/25/jane-jacobs-vancouver/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/25/jane-jacobs-vancouver/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago I saw Geoff Boeing&amp;rsquo;s excellent package to generate Jane Jacobs style street grid images. It&amp;rsquo;s lots of fun to compare different cities that way.
It can be hard to represent one city by one square mile, so I thought it would be neat to use this to compare different parts of Vancouver. Some common themes emerge for the central parts, the more outlying areas display very differnet patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bumper Year for Thumb Twiddlers</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/18/bumper-year-for-thumb-twiddlers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/18/bumper-year-for-thumb-twiddlers/</guid>
      <description>Almost a year has passed since we first noticed how sitting on single family homes and twiddling thumbs generates more income than working. And not just at the level of individual single family households. In the City of Vancouver, the cumulative land value gains of just the single family homes eclipsed the cumulative taxable earnings reported to the CRA for the entire population.
With the new assessment data available now, it is time to run the numbers and see how our thumb-twiddlers fared vs workers this year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Coveted $1.2m - $1.6m Vote</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/17/the-coveted-2m-6m-vote/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/17/the-coveted-2m-6m-vote/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this month the province increased the threshold for the homeowner grant from $1.2 million to $1.6 million dollars. It&amp;rsquo;s an election year, and with the BC Assessment data for the City of Vancouver now being available via their open data catalogue we can ask who exactly this move was targeting.
Restricted to the City of Vancouver, the answer is quite simple. There are about 24,000 single family homes, 1,200 duplex units and 4,000 condo units in that bracket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 Vancouver Assessment Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/16/2017-assessment-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/01/16/2017-assessment-data/</guid>
      <description>The friendly folks at Vancouver Open Data just updated their property assessment data with the fresh 2017 property tax assessments. Time to run the script to update the Vancouver Assessment Map with the new data, just like we did last year.
For now we just updated our standard visuals and computed some overall statistics. We will take a closer look at the data over the coming days.
Maps  By now we have a variety of maps that highlight different aspects of Vancouver real estate, and after running the import scripts they automatically serve the newest data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated Property Tax Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/12/13/updated-property-tax-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/12/13/updated-property-tax-data/</guid>
      <description>The property tax data for the City of Vancouver has been available for a while now, and with new assessment data becoming available soon everyone&amp;rsquo;s worried about what their property taxes will look like. The City just passed a 3.9% increase in their budget, so on average everyone will pay 3.9% more taxes than they did last year.
The exact change in property taxes varies from property to property. There is a nice overview on how this works in general, for the City of Vancouver there is an added complication of land value averaging meant to soften sudden land value increases, that effectively serves to lower taxes for single family homeowners in a rising market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Character Retention</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/11/26/character-retention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/11/26/character-retention/</guid>
      <description>Today I went to the City of Vancouver Character Retention open house. It was quite informative, city staff were helpful and knowledgeable, and the display board and feedback form asked many good questions. But I came away with a couple of points that I think need to be addressed further:
Faux character retention vs character design guidelines.  Understanding economic drivers of teardown decisions. Evaluation of RT character retention policies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secondary Suites and Taxes</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/10/04/secondary-suites-and-taxes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/10/04/secondary-suites-and-taxes/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I started thinking about secondary suites, laneway houses and taxes in the City of Vancouver. The number of secondary suites and laneway houses has been continuously growing. Rental income is probably one of the main reasons people choose to activate a secondary suite. What are the tax implications?
Secondary Suites How many secondary suites are out there? Nobody really knows, but we have some estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Housing Affordability</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/09/14/measuring-housing-affordability/</guid>
      <description>Housing affordability is a serious issue that deserves attention. Affordability is generally defined comparing incomes to housing costs. And ideally also factoring in transportation cost, although that&amp;rsquo;s seldom done and we will not attempt today.
Recently we took a detailed look at income data. Using what we learned, together with our detailed data on the development of prices of single family properties in Vancouver, we turn to the never dying question of affordability of single family homes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Guide to Income Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/31/incomes/</guid>
      <description>The news media has an extraordinarily difficult time with income data. And that&amp;rsquo;s only partially the media&amp;rsquo;s fault. In general, income data is a funny beast. So I decided to give a quick overview over income data that&amp;rsquo;s available through Statistics Canada. To make things a little more concrete I focused on Vancouver as an example, but everything applies equally well to any other area in Canada.
Most journalists I talked to care about accurate and relevant statements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobi Running Stats</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/24/mobi-running-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/24/mobi-running-stats/</guid>
      <description>I keep getting questions about Mobi stats these days. Rather than ansering them one by one I decided to just offer a live view into data generated by our shadow API. I made two simple views, the most recent month of daily bike checkout counts and the most recent week of hourly bike checkout counts. The data issues mentioned in our previous post still apply. For data geeks, here is a link to a very useful paper that compared estimates like I make to real usage data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobi -- a First Look</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/16/mobi-a-first-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/16/mobi-a-first-look/</guid>
      <description>Vancouver finally has a bikeshare system. And everyone is hoping it will succeed, despite the obstacles BC&amp;rsquo;s mandatory helmet law poses for the system. So we are eager to find out how things are going with Mobi.
To set the background, consider that Seattle&amp;rsquo;s Pronto is getting less than 1 ride per bike per day after half a year in operation. In comparison, bike shares that are considered &amp;lsquo;successful&amp;rsquo; in North America get 3 to 5 rides per bike per day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s up with RT?</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/04/rt/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/08/04/rt/</guid>
      <description>RT is Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s zoning for duplexes. Over time, various areas have been zoned to allow duplexes. Examples are Kits Point, much of Point Grey Road reaching up to Broadway, much of Granview-Woodlands, parts of Mount Pleasant and many other areas.
Recently I have had some interesting conversations on Twitter regarding RM-6 and over BBQ dinner about RT-7. Then the Granview-Woodland plan passed by council, and it contains a curious provision of reducing the outright FSR for the RT-zoned properties from 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Share Map</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/26/bike-share-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/26/bike-share-map/</guid>
      <description>It is no secret that we at MountainMath like bikes. And maps. And open data and sharing. We guess you know where this is going.
Vancouver has finally gotten a bike share system, and we are loving it. So we took the occasion to take our old bike infrastructure maps, polished them up a bit using Mapzen&amp;rsquo;s bike map style and adapted it for our purposes.
The result is our Vancouver Bike Share Map.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mixing Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/07/06/mixing-data/</guid>
      <description>Census data is very rich and with CensusMapper we now have about 1 billion data points right at our fingertips. And we have managed to open up some of our interfaces for everyone to explore data and make their own maps and freely share them.
Things really get interesting when one mixes custom data with census data. While, at this point, these are not part of the freely available CensusMapper functionality we still wanted to share what can be done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDH Zoning and Land Use</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/</guid>
      <description>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my Twitter feed citing that SFH take up 70%, 66%, and 57%, 56% (timestamp 3:50). I personally have thrown in 34% as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FSR</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I played with the LIDAR-generated building height data I thought that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three. Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Global Bike Map</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/16/my-global-bike-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/16/my-global-bike-map/</guid>
      <description>Last week Mapzen announced that they included bike data in their OSM vector tiles. That&amp;rsquo;s just what the doctor ordered to continue on my path towards the perfect bike map that I started on, explored routing and looked at improving OSM bike data. Now that I don&amp;rsquo;t need to extract bike data myself any more it is time to take these maps global. And maybe add some minor improvements.
To make the bike map boils down to deciding what OSM roads, paths, etc to map and how to map them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Mapping for Everyone</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/04/census-mapping-for-everyone/</guid>
      <description>At CensusMapper, we have come a long way from first dabbling in census data to building out a platform to map data Canada wide, adding the ability to easily drill down into individual census regions, improving mapping efficiency, adding the ability to automatically populate custom geographic data with census variables and adding older census data.
We believe all of these are comparatively small steps compared to the opening up of map making capabilities for everyone that we are rolling out today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Week</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/02/census-week/</guid>
      <description>At CensusMapper we are super excited about Census Week 2016. Data is increasingly getting incorporated into local and regional decision making. At CensusMapper we have been working to facilitate this by making this wealth of information more accessible to everyone. To celebrate Census Week 2016 we have updated CensusMapper with 2006 census data for easy comparisons with the 2011 data. And we have given CensusMapper a face lift by adding a histogram widget that interacts with the mapping data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TOD Mode Share</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/20/tod-mode-share/</guid>
      <description>Just saw a comment on the Pricetags blog pointing to a nice master&amp;rsquo;s thesis investigating various TOD metrics around skytrain stations. I got curious how the 2011 transit mode share compares to the earlier census years listed in the thesis. And how the mode share varies spatially.
With CensusMapper at my finger tips and building on the visuals from the previous post this is an easy exercise.
We again simply map our concentric circles around the stations, but this time we turn them into pie charts to show the commute to work mode share.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TOD</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/06/tod/</guid>
      <description>Just saw this excellent post looking at density around transit stations today and though I should pull out some numbers to go with the pretty visuals. And with CensusMapper&amp;rsquo;s new capabilities of populating custom geometries with census data estimates it&amp;rsquo;s super-easy to do.
Population density is only one measure of interest here, job density or amenities density would be others. But for now let&amp;rsquo;s focus on population, so how many people live near the rapid transit stations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Houses and Dirt</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/04/01/on-dirt-and-houses/</guid>
      <description>The story of Vancouver real estate is mostly a story of dirt. After spending a bit of time to collect relevant data I am now wondering how to make better visualizations to make that data more accessible.
 Looking at my old maps based around assessment data, there are a couple of things that bother me. They are not very good at showing changes over time. And they are not very good at highlighting the different role of dirt and the houses on top.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Mixed Use</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/28/on-mixed-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/28/on-mixed-use/</guid>
      <description>Redeveloping single storey commercial properties into mixed use is taking off in Vancouver right now. It&amp;rsquo;s a little frustrating to see how pretty much every story I have seen on this get the effect this has on property taxes wrong, including one on the generally quite good Price Tags blog. People claim that converting single story commercial to mixed use pushes up the property taxes for the commercial tenants. Property taxes are an important piece of the puzzle in Vancouver, so I decided to go into a little detail on this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surrey Traffic Loop Counts</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/27/surrey-traffic-loop-counts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/27/surrey-traffic-loop-counts/</guid>
      <description>Surrey published a beta version of their traffic loop counts, which is pretty awesome. Real life traffic data is very exciting, and there are lots of fun things one could do with that. So last night I decided to take a look and make a quick map. Nothing exciting yet, just to feel may way around what&amp;rsquo;s there. To keep things simple I again took advantage of the awesome Tangram mapping enginge and turned it onto the traffic loop data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unoccupied Dwellings</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/08/unoccupied-dwellings/</guid>
      <description>Today the City of Vancouver released their report on unoccupied dwelling units in the city. I watched part of the presentation and read through the report, and from all that I can see the methodology used is very solid.
I have seen some confusion and even some incorrect reporting on this, so I thought it would be worthwhile to look into the report in detail. The Data Smart meter data can be used to determine very accurately which units are occupied and which ones are not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physical SFH Form Over Time</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/05/physical-sfh-form-over-time/</guid>
      <description>I was curious how the physical parameters of Single Family Houses changed over time.
Using the assessment dataset merged with the land use dataset allows to fairly accurately pick out single family houses, and also holds the age of most properies. Together with the City of Vancouver LIDAR-generated building dataset that I have played with before we can look at physical building parameters.
The city dataset is a little coarse, it only contains the main building and does not map things like garages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Property Taxes and Land Use</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use/</guid>
      <description>Since I started thinking about tax density, the amount of property taxes collected per area, I always felt that the data presentation in the map fell short.
Property taxes are somewhat insulated from the ups and downs of the real estate market as they are need-based and the mill rate changes to flatten out the crazyness of the market. But what they lack in interesting patterns over time they more than makes up for in interesting patterns in space.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Land Use, Roads (and Parking)</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/29/land-use/</guid>
      <description>The other day at the SFU&amp;rsquo;s City Conversations someone asked a question about space dedicated to roads, and how that could be unlocked to aid housing. He mentioned what percentage of space is currently dedicated to roads. I forgot the number, but I thought to myself that I should look that up for all Metro Vancouver communities. So here we go. Actually, it would be interesting to compare how land is allocated to all kinds of land uses across Metro Vancouver, not just roads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Condos</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/10/on-condos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2016 11:01:47 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/10/on-condos/</guid>
      <description>Lots has been said about the upper end of owned dwellings. The movement of the &amp;ldquo;million dollar line&amp;rdquo;, the emergence of the &amp;ldquo;two million dollar line&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;multi-million dollar lines&amp;rdquo;. Most of that discussion is focused on single detached homes or on proxies for &amp;ldquo;single detached&amp;rdquo; like RS zoned properties.
But all of these maps have a clear bias toward the more expensive homes. Everyone knows by now where the most expensive properties are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Loss of Character</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/01/loss-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/02/01/loss-of-character/</guid>
      <description>At the heart of the Vancouver affordability crisis is a phrase that comes up again and again. Loss of Character. To effectively move forward I think it is important to look closely what it means and how it is used.
And what the data can tell us about loss of character. Loss of Character Very broadly interpreted, change of character is how people describe the process when the environment around them is changing in profound ways.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Land Use Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/31/land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/31/land-use/</guid>
      <description>Metro Vancouver has a fairly good land use dataset that I imported quite some time ago so that I could take a good look at it. But then I forgot about it until @HealthyCityMaps reminded me just at the time when the discussions about assessmened values in Vancouver were flaring up again.
So finally I decided to mark up the City of Vancouver assessment dataset with the land use from the Metro Vancouver land use dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work vs Twiddling Thumbs</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/24/work-vs-twiddling-thumbs/</guid>
      <description>In the ongoing debate on affordability of housing in the City of Vancouver we regularly hear voices expressing concern for &amp;ldquo;elderly folks of modest means who had been counting on using their home as a pension&amp;rdquo; to argue against doing anything to ease the housing affordability problems many (younger) people are facing. In these arguments the concern for &amp;ldquo;elderly folks of modest means&amp;rdquo; seems curiously focused to those who own property as opposed to, for example, the 20% of the elderly people in Vancouver that live in poverty (15k total).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Teardowns</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/18/redevelopment/</guid>
      <description>On the heels of the new assessment data we can start to slice the data in different ways to understand various aspects of the real estate landscape in Vancouver. The fact that Vancouver Open Data makes historic data available gives the ability to look for changes over time.
Our maps explore this by visualizing some aspects of these changes for all properties, but it might also be useful to filter the properties we show to focus in on specific criteria.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated Vancouver Assessment Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/01/17/updated-vancouver-assessment-data/</guid>
      <description>The friendly folks at Vancouver Open Data just updated their property assessment data with the fresh 2016 property tax assessments. Time to run the script to update the Vancouver Assessment Map with the new data. And for good measure I pasted over some of the thematic map engine from CensusMapper to improve the mapping performance.
Maps The interactive assessment map offers several views. In the panel on the top right we can select how to view the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Canvas vs SVG</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/27/canvas-vs-svg/</guid>
      <description>CensusMapper Behind the Scenes The idea behind CensusMapper is that it takes away all the technical barriers to dealing with census data. So how does CensusMapper work behind the scenes?
CensusMapper Data Workflow The general setup is quite simple. We use the lean javascript open mapping platform leaflet as the base for mapping information. Leaflet handles the logic of dealing with zoom and pan and keeping track of the geographic boundaries that should be mapped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/15/bike-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/15/bike-data/</guid>
      <description>Maps live and die with the quality of the underlying data. So I decided to dive a little deeper down the OSM bike data rabbit hole. Task number one was to expand display data for a wider region. My primitive workflow to pull data out of OSM only allows for extracting a quarter of a degree at a time. For playing around with all of Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s data I again turned to Mapzen for their metro extracts as a convenient shortcut for OSM data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Routing</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/14/routing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/14/routing/</guid>
      <description>Routing is a hard problem. Routing for drivers is pretty good at this point, mostly because we have been very good at designing for cars and creating predicable infrastructure. Routing for bikes is a whole other story, data quality is poor and the physical infrastructure is, at least in North America, not strongly predictive of cycling comfort/safety. And cycling comfort/safety is the top priority for the vast majority of (potential) cyclists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make a bike map</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/13/how-to-make-a-bike-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/12/13/how-to-make-a-bike-map/</guid>
      <description>Here come some general thoughts on bike maps. Not throught through yet, just jotting down some ideas so that I don&amp;rsquo;t forget and maybe to start a discussion.
Bike enthusiasts, OSM folks and mapping technology wonks read on! Why make a new bike map? Plainly put, I don&amp;rsquo;t like a lot of the bike maps out there. Time for my little bike map rant:
 Lots of maps don&amp;rsquo;t accomplish their core mission: accurately map bike infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Drilldown</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/10/24/census-drilldown/</guid>
      <description>Next steps in CensusMapper The Census Mapper Project is moving along slowly, public beta unearthed some bugs and we gathered feedback (thanks to everyone reporting back!). There are still a couple of steps that need to be taken care of before we can unleash the full map making power to all users. We feel that the complexity of census data requires more guidance than the current map making system is providing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Census Mapper</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/09/28/census-mapper/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce CensusMapper public beta launch! The project on mapping census data for Canada is entering the next stage. We are now mapping 3875 different variables from the 2011 census, or any combination of them, across 67215 geographic regions covering all of Canada.
We are opening up the Census Mapper to a limited public beta. Limited means that anyone can view maps created in CensusMapper, but we are only opening up the map creation tools to selected beta users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hidden Mortgage</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/08/25/the-hidden-mortgage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/08/25/the-hidden-mortgage/</guid>
      <description>Some months ago I did a little side project and put some Census Canada data for Vancouver on an interactive map online. After it generated quite some interest, to a large part due to Ian Young&amp;rsquo;s reporting utilizing some of the data in the South China Morning Post, I talked to my friend Alejandro and we decided to set up a Census Mapper that allowes laymen to map any census variables of their choosing Canada wide.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vancouver 2011 Census Data on Housing</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/06/23/vancouver-2011-census-data-on-housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/06/23/vancouver-2011-census-data-on-housing/</guid>
      <description>Last week my friend Alejandro emailed me some census data. After sitting on it for a couple of days I decided one evening to take a look and map the dissemination areas. The dataset contained 125 fields around housing and income. So I started plucking some of the fields off the table and mapping them.
It did not take long and colorful maps started showing up. Another evening and lots of map layers later I put the Vancouver Census Map online for people interested to look through the census graphs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tax Density in Vancouver</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/05/31/density-in-vancouver/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/05/31/density-in-vancouver/</guid>
      <description>The other day I saw that Downtown brings in 23% of CoV tax revenue but only makes up 5% of the city area. Intrigued by that I decided to add a &amp;lsquo;Tax Density&amp;rsquo; layer to my Vancouver Assessment Map. The idea was to try and understand the tax revenue generated by different areas in Vancouver. The data is already available in the CoV open data property dataset so it would only take half an hour to ad it to my map.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vancouver Bike Paths</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/04/01/bike-paths/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/04/01/bike-paths/</guid>
      <description>Motivated by the excellent Washington Post Wonkblog I mapped Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s bike infrastructure. Looks good at first, but when you take out the &amp;lsquo;fake&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;Local Street&amp;rdquo; bikeways more in line with Wonkblog&amp;rsquo;s methodology it&amp;rsquo;s looking pretty bleak in large portions of the city.
Of course the devil is in the details and infrastructure cannot just be judged by how it&amp;rsquo;s labeled. If one were to look for 8-80 infrastructure, then the separated lanes would make the cut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vancouver Assessment Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/03/23/vancouver-assessment-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/03/23/vancouver-assessment-data/</guid>
      <description>The City of Vancouver has recently updated their open data catalogue with historic tax data. We figured that would be a good time to take our previous rather clumsy attempts to map tax data and polish that up a bit.
This time we put in a couple of evenings to build a more responsive map with multiple options of what to map. Head straight for &amp;lsquo;the map&amp;rsquo; or read on for some background information, including some methodology on data cleaning and interpolation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping CACs</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/11/05/mapping-cacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/11/05/mapping-cacs/</guid>
      <description>After reading the post on Price Tags, originally from Karen Sawatzky&amp;rsquo;s blog, I got curious about getting a geographic overview over the CACs in Vancouver in 2010, 2011 and 2012.
As opposed to the teardown map the dataset is quite small, so there should be no problems viewing this on a mobile device. As always, map is below the fold.
Some of the property addresses did not match any address in the CoV open data property database, probably because the developments are quite new and new addresses got assigned.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vancouver High Value Improvements Map</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/07/vancouver-high-value-improvements-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/07/vancouver-high-value-improvements-map/</guid>
      <description>After the teardown map that looked at the low end of Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s building stock, a natural question is to look at the high end. Just as before, we are focusing on the (assessed) value of the building relative to the total (assessed) value of land and improvements. We defined &amp;ldquo;highly improved&amp;rdquo; properties to be properties where the ratio is at least 50%, so the building is worth at least as much as the land it is built on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vancouver Teardown Map</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/05/vancouver-teardown-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2014/09/05/vancouver-teardown-map/</guid>
      <description>There has been lots of talk about old homes being torn down and replaced in Vancouver. The likeliest targets are houses of relatively low value sitting on expensive land. So how many teardown candidates are there in Vancouver, and where in Vancouver are they located?
To answer this we use data from Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s open data catalogue to build an interactive map to explore the low end of the building stock. More specifically, we set a somewhat arbitrary ratio of (assessed) house value to total (assessed) property value (house + land) of 5% and label everything below that a &amp;ldquo;teardown candidate&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>