<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Density on Mountain Doodles</title>
    <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/categories/density/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Density on Mountain Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/categories/density/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Density</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2017/08/23/density/</guid>
      <description>Density in Vancouver has been one of the recurring themese on this blog, and there are many different ways to come at it. We have looked at density in terms of land use to understand how much land is devoted to what purpose in Metro Vancouver and it&amp;rsquo;s municipalities. We have looked at density in terms of tax density to understand how property tax revenue depends on land use and zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated Property Tax Data</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/12/13/updated-property-tax-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/12/13/updated-property-tax-data/</guid>
      <description>The property tax data for the City of Vancouver has been available for a while now, and with new assessment data becoming available soon everyone&amp;rsquo;s worried about what their property taxes will look like. The City just passed a 3.9% increase in their budget, so on average everyone will pay 3.9% more taxes than they did last year.
The exact change in property taxes varies from property to property. There is a nice overview on how this works in general, for the City of Vancouver there is an added complication of land value averaging meant to soften sudden land value increases, that effectively serves to lower taxes for single family homeowners in a rising market.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDH Zoning and Land Use</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/06/17/sdh-zoning-and-land-use/</guid>
      <description>Recently the question around the amount of space taken up (exclusively) by single detached houses has show up on my Twitter feed citing that SFH take up 70%, 66%, and 57%, 56% (timestamp 3:50). I personally have thrown in 34% as a contender. And, just for the fun of it, by the end of this post I will have thrown 33% and 28% and my favorite, 81%, into the mix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FSR</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2016/05/20/density/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I played with the LIDAR-generated building height data I thought that I should use that to map gross floor area (GFA) and floor space ratio (FSR). Gross floor area is the total floor area inside the building envelope. So for a three storey building, it is the area of the footprint times three. Floor space ratio is the GFA divided by the area of the parcel it sits on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tax Density in Vancouver</title>
      <link>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/05/31/density-in-vancouver/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://doodles.mountainmath.ca/blog/2015/05/31/density-in-vancouver/</guid>
      <description>The other day I saw that Downtown brings in 23% of CoV tax revenue but only makes up 5% of the city area. Intrigued by that I decided to add a &amp;lsquo;Tax Density&amp;rsquo; layer to my Vancouver Assessment Map. The idea was to try and understand the tax revenue generated by different areas in Vancouver. The data is already available in the CoV open data property dataset so it would only take half an hour to ad it to my map.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>