<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mapzen on Mountain Doodles</title>
    <link>/categories/mapzen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mapzen on Mountain Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/mapzen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Transit Explorer</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/03/01/transit-explorer/</guid>
      <description>I have played with Mapzen&amp;rsquo;s Isochrone serivce in the past with a simple visualization of walksheds.
Recently Mazen updated the isochrone API to allow for a more fine-grained selection of exactly what transit services to include or exclude in transit routing, and they created an amazing mobility explorer based on that.
Partially motivated by chatting with two TransLink planners I decided to riff off of that and take a look at how well TransLink serves different parts of Vancouver.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Isochrones</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/11/18/interactive-isochrones/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/11/18/interactive-isochrones/</guid>
      <description>Mapzen again upped their game by publishing their Mobility API. This is super exciting for anyone interested in a whole range of mobility questions. A question I have seen is how to adapt that to specific needs. So here is a quick example how to customize walksheds.
All we do is set up a quick map that computes the 5 and 10 minute walksheds when the user clicks on the map.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sea Level Rise</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/10/02/sea-level-rise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/10/02/sea-level-rise/</guid>
      <description>Sea level rise comes up regularly in coastal cities. And nowadays every costal area, including Vancouver has their flood assessment and detailed plans on how to deal with sea level rise, although some plans are more interesting than others.
The web is awash with sea level rise maps, some static, some interactive, some global ones and some national maps. Data sources range from high detail LIDAR data to satellite data and other datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobi Running Stats</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/08/24/mobi-running-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/08/24/mobi-running-stats/</guid>
      <description>I keep getting questions about Mobi stats these days. Rather than ansering them one by one I decided to just offer a live view into data generated by our shadow API. I made two simple views, the most recent month of daily bike checkout counts and the most recent week of hourly bike checkout counts. The data issues mentioned in our previous post still apply. For data geeks, here is a link to a very useful paper that compared estimates like I make to real usage data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobi -- a First Look</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/08/16/mobi-a-first-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/08/16/mobi-a-first-look/</guid>
      <description>Vancouver finally has a bikeshare system. And everyone is hoping it will succeed, despite the obstacles BC&amp;rsquo;s mandatory helmet law poses for the system. So we are eager to find out how things are going with Mobi.
To set the background, consider that Seattle&amp;rsquo;s Pronto is getting less than 1 ride per bike per day after half a year in operation. In comparison, bike shares that are considered &amp;lsquo;successful&amp;rsquo; in North America get 3 to 5 rides per bike per day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Share Map</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/07/26/bike-share-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/07/26/bike-share-map/</guid>
      <description>It is no secret that we at MountainMath like bikes. And maps. And open data and sharing. We guess you know where this is going.
Vancouver has finally gotten a bike share system, and we are loving it. So we took the occasion to take our old bike infrastructure maps, polished them up a bit using Mapzen&amp;rsquo;s bike map style and adapted it for our purposes.
The result is our Vancouver Bike Share Map.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Global Bike Map</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/05/16/my-global-bike-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/05/16/my-global-bike-map/</guid>
      <description>Last week Mapzen announced that they included bike data in their OSM vector tiles. That&amp;rsquo;s just what the doctor ordered to continue on my path towards the perfect bike map that I started on, explored routing and looked at improving OSM bike data. Now that I don&amp;rsquo;t need to extract bike data myself any more it is time to take these maps global. And maybe add some minor improvements.
To make the bike map boils down to deciding what OSM roads, paths, etc to map and how to map them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Property Taxes and Land Use</title>
      <link>/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016/03/02/property-taxes-and-land-use/</guid>
      <description>Since I started thinking about tax density, the amount of property taxes collected per area, I always felt that the data presentation in the map fell short.
Property taxes are somewhat insulated from the ups and downs of the real estate market as they are need-based and the mill rate changes to flatten out the crazyness of the market. But what they lack in interesting patterns over time they more than makes up for in interesting patterns in space.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Routing</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/12/14/routing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/12/14/routing/</guid>
      <description>Routing is a hard problem. Routing for drivers is pretty good at this point, mostly because we have been very good at designing for cars and creating predicable infrastructure. Routing for bikes is a whole other story, data quality is poor and the physical infrastructure is, at least in North America, not strongly predictive of cycling comfort/safety. And cycling comfort/safety is the top priority for the vast majority of (potential) cyclists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make a bike map</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/12/13/how-to-make-a-bike-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/12/13/how-to-make-a-bike-map/</guid>
      <description>Here come some general thoughts on bike maps. Not throught through yet, just jotting down some ideas so that I don&amp;rsquo;t forget and maybe to start a discussion.
Bike enthusiasts, OSM folks and mapping technology wonks read on! Why make a new bike map? Plainly put, I don&amp;rsquo;t like a lot of the bike maps out there. Time for my little bike map rant:
 Lots of maps don&amp;rsquo;t accomplish their core mission: accurately map bike infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>